Analyzing modules 575 to 577...

======================================================
MODULE 575: Basics of Neonatology and Routine Newborn Care (80 questions)
======================================================
ID: 23285 | Ans (C): Cephalohematoma
  Q: A 28-day-old child was brought to the OPD with swelling over the head since birth. What is the diagnosis?
  Expl snippet: The X-ray image shows blood collection in scalp tissue, not extending intracranially. Encephalocele gets ruled out since...
ID: 23286 | Ans (A): Swelling of the soft tissue of scalp
  Q: A newborn comes to you on 2nd day of life with following finding. The child was delivered by normal vaginal delivery wit
  Expl snippet: The child in the image has It is a subperiosteal hemorrhage . The closest differential diagnosis is caput succedaneum. I...
ID: 23287 | Ans (B): Golden yellow
  Q: What is the normal color of stool in the newborn after first week of life?
  Topic Tag: MISCELLANEOUS Difficulty level: GOOD TO KNOW Reference: Ghai essential pediatrics, 9 th ed, pg no: 133
  Expl snippet: Meconium (first stool) is passed within 24 hours. After that meconium stools (black tarry)can be passed upto 3 days. On ...
ID: 23288 | Ans (C): Right Upper limb
  Q: A newborn baby presents to the hospital with the presence of a continuous machine-like murmur. In such cases, the assess
  Expl snippet: ...
ID: 23289 | Ans (C): 65%
  Q: What is the venous hematocrit level at which you will diagnose polycythemia in a newborn?
  Expl snippet: Definition of polycythemia: a. Venous haematocrit of over 65%. b. Venous haematocrit of over 64% at 2 hours age. c. An u...
ID: 23290 | Ans (B): HALE
  Q: DALE is replaced by ?
  Expl snippet: Ans. is 'b' i.e., HALE [Ref Park 20th/e p. 24] HALE (Health - Adjusted life expectancy) :- The name of the indicator use...
ID: 23291 | Ans (D): 2, 3, 4
  Q: You have to IV cannulate a newborn. The following things are available: 1. 22 G Cannula 2. 26 G Cannula 3. Gloves 4. Nor
  Expl snippet: This question is a practical application-based question and very similar to an actual question asked recently. The corre...
ID: 23292 | Ans (A): Saline-soaked gauze
  Q: In a neonate with leaky meningomyelocele with CSF dripping out, it should be covered with which among the following befo
  Expl snippet: The exposed meningomyelocele sac containing neural tissue should be covered with a sterile Saline-soaked gauze. REMEMBER...
ID: 23293 | Ans (B): Neuroblastoma
  Q: Dinutuximab has been recently approved for which among the following pediatric malignancy?
  Expl snippet: Dinutuximab is a monoclonal antibody that targets a diasialoganglioside, GD2, which has ubiquitous expression on neurobl...
ID: 23294 | Ans (B): Order urgent bronchoscopy to remove fore
  Q: A 2-year-old boy presents to the ED with shortness of breath in mild distress. His parents state that they were at a mov
  Expl snippet: The chest x-ray shows hyperinflation of the left side and a mediastinal shift to the right , which should raise suspicio...
ID: 23295 | Ans (C): >2500 grams
  Q: A baby receiving KMC is now stable enough for the procedure to be stopped. What shall be the baby's weight at which you 
  Expl snippet: When to Discontinue KMC? If the mother and baby are comfortable, KMC is continued at the hospital and at home for as lon...
ID: 23296 | Ans (C): Check creatine kinase level
  Q: A 7-month-old male infant is at his pediatrician's office for his routine check-up and immunizations. He can roll over f
  Expl snippet: This infant has development delay predominantly involving motor domain with history of maternal uncle dying between 15-2...
ID: 23297 | Ans (C): 6 months
  Q: An anxious mother of a 3-day newborn, comes to you for a routine visit. While counselling about the weight gain pattern 
  Expl snippet: The weight of the baby doubles by 6 months. Tags : Topic : GROWTH & ANTHROPOMETRY Difficulty level : MUST KNOW PYQ : INI...
ID: 23298 | Ans (C): Supplementary nutrition
  Q: Which of the following is not a component of Kangaroo Mother Care (KMC)?
  Expl snippet: Components of KMC have traditionally included the following 3 things In the latest AIIMS Protocol 2023, 3 rd Edition, a ...
ID: 23299 | Ans (D): Osmotic fragility
  Q: A newborn female develops jaundice at 12 hours of life. Her indirect bilirubin is 21.2 mg/dL. His mother's blood type is
  Topic Tag: ANEMIA Difficulty level: GOOD TO KNOW PYQ: NEET PG 2023 Reference: Nelson textbook of Pediatrics, 1 st SA edition, page number: 2330
  Expl snippet: The patient has hereditary spherocytosis, which can be confirmed by osmotic fragility testing. Osmotic Fragility Test: S...
ID: 23302 | Ans (C): Donor human milk
  Q: A preterm neonate could not be started on mother's feed due to some maternal issues. Which among the following is the be
  Expl snippet: DONOR HUMAN MILK Donar human milk [DHM] is the milk expressed and voluntarily donated by lactating women other than the ...
ID: 23304 | Ans (D): Pyloric atresia
  Q: You are called by the newborn nursery nurse secondary to see a 1-day-old infant vomiting with every feed. The patient ta
  Expl snippet: It is a tough question, but such questions can be answered by ruling out other options easily. Option A- Pyloric stenosi...
ID: 23306 | Ans (D): Erythromycin only
  Q: Ajay, a 3-year-old child, is the younger brother of Anuj, who is currently undergoing treatment for diphtheria in the ho
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Ajay is a household contact of a diphtheria case and should receive erythromycin prophylaxis, even though h...
ID: 23307 | Ans (C): Remand homes
  Q: Homes where children are placed under the care of doctors and psychiatrists are called -
  Expl snippet: Ans. is 'c' i.e., Remand homes Child placement : o Orphanages : For children who have no home or cannot be taken care of...
ID: 23308 | Ans (B): 400 IU/day
  Q: What is the current IAP recommendation for Vitamin D3 supplementation in a full-term neonate?
  Expl snippet: All infants younger than 12 months should receive 400 IU daily beginning within the first few days after birth. Healthy ...
ID: 23310 | Ans (D): Raised areola
  Q: While assessing a newborn for maturity, which of the following findings does not suggest prematurity?
  Expl snippet: Commonly assessed components for checking the maturity are: Tags : Topic : NORMAL NEWBORN Difficulty level : MUST KNOW P...
ID: 23311 | Ans (C): 34 w to 36 w 6 d GA
  Q: By definition, what is called as late preterm baby?
  Expl snippet: Preterm are born at . Subgroups of preterm infant include the following: Extremely preterm infants are born Early preter...
ID: 23312 | Ans (B): Anemia
  Q: In a monochorionic monoamniotic twin with uncompensated arteriovenous shunt, which of the following characteristic is pr
  Expl snippet: Monochorionic twin with uncompensated arteriovenous shunt has following differentiating features : Tags : Topic : HIGH R...
ID: 23313 | Ans (A): Stage 1
  Q: A full-term newborn has history of delayed cry and suspected hypoxic ischemic encephalopathy. The baby is hyperalert wit
  Expl snippet: Important points from SARNAT and SARNAT staging for HIE Tags : Topic : HYPOXIC ISCHEMIC ENCEPHALOPATHY Difficulty level ...
ID: 23314 | Ans (A): Damage to C5-C6
  Q: A 4kg post term baby is delivered at 43weeks of gestation with difficult vaginal delivery. Forceps assistance was needed
  Expl snippet: The child in the question has Erb's palsy. Cause: excessive traction on the head, neck and arm during birth. Risk factor...
ID: 23315 | Ans (C): Administer IV glucose and recheck blood 
  Q: A newborn, born to a diabetic mother, presents after 24 hours with a blood glucose (BG) < 35 mg/dl. The baby is symptoma
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Neonatal hypoglycemia is defined as BG In an infant of a diabetic mother , hyperinsulinemia predisposes to ...
ID: 23316 | Ans (B): Oropharyngeal airway
  Q: A newborn presents with irritability and cyanosis that improves with crying. On examination, a nasogastric tube cannot b
  Expl snippet: Explanation: The patient's presentations are suggestive of choanal atresia and the next best step in management is estab...
ID: 23317 | Ans (D): C5-C6
  Q: A newborn developed an asymmetric Moro reflex after a complicated delivery. The poorly responsive arm hung in adduction,
  Expl snippet: The patient described in this case has the classic signs of Erb's palsy, a paralysis of the muscles innervated by the C5...
ID: 23318 | Ans (A): Gilbert syndrome
  Q: An 8-day-old infant continues to have jaundice which was first noted on the second day of life; his latest total and dir
  Expl snippet: This is a neonate with unconjugated hyperbilirubinemia and raised reticulocyte count & negative Coombs test. Gilbert syn...
ID: 23319 | Ans (D): Chromosome 22
  Q: A 2-day-old baby boy is admitted at the neonatal intensive care unit due to high fever with a temperature of 38&#176;C a
  Expl snippet: Clues in the question include facial dysmorphism, cleft palate, infection causing hospital admission, a likely heart dis...
ID: 23320 | Ans (B): Influenza virus
  Q: A child was advised yearly vaccination with a vaccine, which is not a part of the national immunization schedule. Yearly
  Expl snippet: Annual vaccination is given against Influenza Vaccine in selected high-risk groups. The type of influenza vaccine curren...
ID: 23321 | Ans (D): Back blows with face down
  Q: An 11-month-old male is found by his mother at home unconscious and not breathing after she left him eating in the room.
  Expl snippet: The management of FB aspiration depends on the presentation and age of the patient. For infants under the age of 1 year,...
ID: 23322 | Ans (D): Chromosome 22
  Q: A 2-day-old baby boy is admitted at the neonatal intensive care unit due to high fever with a temperature of 38&deg;C an
  Expl snippet: The boy presents with common manifestations of DiGeorge syndrome. Its pathophysiology involves microdeletions of specifi...
ID: 23323 | Ans (D): < 60/min
  Q: In newborn, chest compression should be started if heart rate is ?
  Expl snippet: Ans, D. < 60/min Compression for new born should be started if HR < 60/min'...
ID: 23324 | Ans (D): <40
  Q: In acute intrinsic renal failure, the urine-to-plasma creatinine ratio is?
  Expl snippet: The urine-to-plasma creatinine ratio is > 40 in prerenal failure. In acute intrinsic renal failure, urine-to-plasma crea...
ID: 23325 | Ans (B): Reassurance that this is self-limited
  Q: A healthy 9-month-old female infant is seen for a routine health supervision visit. On physical examination, a membrane 
  Expl snippet: As seen in the image, the child is having labial adhesions. Asymptomatic children with labial adhesions do not require t...
ID: 23326 | Ans (A): Multicystic Dysplastic Kidney
  Q: Which among the following is the most common cause of abdominal mass in a neonate?
  Expl snippet: Multicystic dysplastic kidney- MCDK is the most common cause of an abdominal mass in the newborn, but the vast majority ...
ID: 23327 | Ans (C): 0.8-1.0 mg/dl
  Q: What is the normal value of creatinine on first day of life in a full term baby?
  Topic Tag: ACUTE KIDNEY INJURY Difficulty level: GOOD TO KNOW PYQ: INICET MAY 2022 Reference: Cloherty and Stark's manual of newborn care, SA ed., pg. 308
  Expl snippet: Normal serum creatinine values at day 1 are 0.8-1.0 mg/dL, 7-0.8 mg/dL at day 3 and Tags: Topic: ACUTE KIDNEY INJURY Dif...
ID: 23333 | Ans (C): SNHL
  Q: A newborn infant on examination was found to be having hepatomegaly. Other examination was normal. On detailed history, 
  Expl snippet: The child has congenital CMV infection. More than 90% babies are asymptomatic. Most common manifestation- Petechial rash...
ID: 23334 | Ans (B): 48 hours
  Q: The mother of a premature newborn is concerned because the baby has not yet passed meconium. What is the maximum safe ti
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Meconium: First stool of the newborn Thick, sticky, greenish-black. Timing: Term newborns: Usually pass mec...
ID: 23335 | Ans (C): Number of daughters a newborn girl will 
  Q: Net reproduction rate is ?
  Expl snippet: Ans. is 'c' i.e., Number of daughters a newborn girl will have during life time Net reproduction rate Net reproductive r...
ID: 23336 | Ans (D): Osmotic fragility
  Q: A newborn female develops jaundice at 12 hours of life. Her indirect bilirubin is 21.2 mg/dL. Her mother's blood type is
  Expl snippet: The patient is a newborn with unconjugated hyperbilirubinemia and low Hb for a neonate. This patient's jaundice is not c...
ID: 23341 | Ans (D): All of the above
  Q: Requirements for IV cannulating a newborn shall include?
  Expl snippet: Cannula size & color IV cannulation a newborn Adequate light Ensure complete aseptic precautions Wear gloves Stabilize c...
ID: 23343 | Ans (B): Large for gestational age
  Q: A neonate was born through normal vaginal delivery at term. His birth weight was 3.8 Kg and was plotted on the chart in 
  Expl snippet: As seen in the image, the birth weight of the neonate has been plotted on the Lubchenco's Chart & since it is above 90 t...
ID: 23344 | Ans (A): Resting heart rate
  Q: All of the following can be used to differentiate a term and preterm baby except?
  Expl snippet: Resting heart rate can't distinguish between term and preterm neonates Regarding other options Expanded new ballard scor...
ID: 23347 | Ans (D): Decreased glycogen stores
  Q: A 1600-g infant was born at 39 6/7 weeks gestation (via spontaneous vaginal delivery) to a 34-year-old woman with a hist
  Expl snippet: Hypoglycemia is common in small-for-gestational-age (SGA) infants, including the infant in this vignette. Of note, hypog...
ID: 23348 | Ans (D): Eosinophils
  Q: An otherwise healthy 2-day-old infant girl is noted to have multiple erythematous papules with small inflammatory pustul
  Expl snippet: The infant has erythema toxicum neonatorum. This common newborn eruption typically spares the palms, soles, and perioral...
ID: 23351 | Ans (C): Overfeeding
  Q: A 2-week-old boy is brought to the clinic for persistent vomiting. The neonate is exclusively fed a standard cow milk- b
  Topic Tag: GASTROESOPHAGEAL REFLUX Difficulty level: MUST KNOW Reference: Nelson textbook of pediatrics, 21 st ed, pg no: 1935
  Expl snippet: The neonate in the vignette has gastroesophageal reflux (GER) caused by overfeeding. In this condition the child is othe...
ID: 23352 | Ans (C): Iron supplements
  Q: A 2-year-old who has eczema has come for routine check-up. He is noticed to be having pallor. The remainder of his exami
  Topic Tag: ANEMIA Difficulty level: MUST KNOW PYQ: NEET PG 2023;2024 Reference: Nelson textbook of pediatrics, 21 st ed, page number: 2522
  Expl snippet: Iron-deficiency anemia is the most likely diagnosis and iron therapy is indicated. The presence of 'pica' strongly sugge...
ID: 23372 | Ans (B): Subaortic stenosis is almost always reco
  Q: Outflow obstruction from the left ventricle is characterized by the following except:
  Topic Tag: ACYANOTIC CHD Difficulty level: MUST KNOW PYQ: INICET MAY 2024 Reference: Park&rsquo;s Pediatric cardiology, 6 th ed., pg. 131
  Expl snippet: Left cardiac outflow obstruction can present in different ways. Infants presenting in the first 2-3 weeks of life usuall...
ID: 23374 | Ans (D): If mother has IgG positive for CMV, chil
  Q: Which of the following is a true statement about congenital CMV infection?
  Expl snippet: Let us evaluate the options individually Option A is false. About 10% of congenital CMV are symptomatic Option B is fals...
ID: 23377 | Ans (C): 24 months
  Q: The weight of a child is quadrupled the birth weight at?
  Expl snippet: Remember the following Reference: O.P Ghai, 10 th edition, Pages 11-12....
ID: 23378 | Ans (D): Ulnar palmar grasp reflex
  Q: Which among the following is the earliest to appear in a child?
  Expl snippet: Let us evaluate each option sequentially Option A- Incomplete/ immature moro's reflex comes at 32 weeks gestation. In th...
ID: 23379 | Ans (B): Parachute reflex
  Q: Which primitive reflex persists throughout life instead of disappearing?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: The parachute reflex: Appears at 7-8 months of age. Persists throughout life. Trigger: when held in ventral...
ID: 23380 | Ans (C): 2.5 - 2.9 kg
  Q: Mean birth weight in India -
  Expl snippet: Ans. is 'c' i.e., 2.5 - 2.9 kg Mean birth weight in Different parts of the world Region Mean birth weight North America,...
ID: 23381 | Ans (C): Stage 2B
  Q: A 28-week preterm baby developed necrotising enterocolitis. He is found to have visible blood in stools, abdominal wall 
  Expl snippet: Presence of Abdominal Wall Cellulitis & Portal Vein Gas in NEC indicate Stage 2B. Modified Bell's Staging of NEC Referen...
ID: 23407 | Ans (C): Peritoneal lavage and drainage
  Q: Treatment of choice in NEC Stage IIIB in an ELBW neonate who is extremely unstable and has DIC includes?
  Expl snippet: Although Laparotomy with resection of gangrenous bowel and enterostomy formation is the standard procedure in most neona...
ID: 23408 | Ans (C): Prevention of NNJ
  Q: All of the following are indications to use Antenatal Dexamethasone in a lady with preterm labour, except?
  Expl snippet: Antenatal corticosteroid given to pregnant female can prevent 3 problems in preterm neonates RDS or HMD IVH NEC However,...
ID: 23409 | Ans (B): Start BMV
  Q: A preterm neonate, admitted in hospital & receiving Caffeine Citrate becomes suddenly apneic and unresponsive. What is t
  Expl snippet: Any neonate developing apnea due to any reason needs to be immediately managed to prevent mortality. Such neonates need ...
ID: 23411 | Ans (A): Near-infrared spectroscopy
  Q: A preterm neonate is being evaluated for complications. Which of the following is now recommended as a latest clinical t
  Expl snippet: As per the latest AIIMS Protocol, 3 rd edition, Near-infrared spectroscopy (NIRS) is a clinical tool that non-invasively...
ID: 23428 | Ans (D): Immature platelet fraction
  Q: A newborn baby comes to you at 7th day of life with refusal to feeding. Baby also had fever since 2 days and reduced act
  Expl snippet: The primary investigation in a suspected neonatal sepsis screen includes Blood culture (option a) Urine culture (option ...
ID: 23451 | Ans (C): Self-inflating bag attached to an oxygen
  Q: Which of the following is not a suitable method for free flow oxygen delivery to a newborn baby?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: A self-inflating bag is specifically designed to provide positive pressure ventilation (PPV) and is not sui...
ID: 23522 | Ans (A): Zika virus
  Q: Transplacental transmission of the organism given in the image which causes microcephaly in the newborn is?
  Expl snippet: Mother infected with Zika virus, transmitted by Aedes mosquito Infection involves Hofbauer cells in placenta Virus cross...
ID: 23617 | Ans (B): Giving a bath immediately after birth
  Q: Which of the following is considered harmful to a newborn in the immediate postnatal period?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Newborns should not be bathed immediately after birth , as it increases the risk of hypothermia, hypoglycem...
ID: 23619 | Ans (D): Prematurity
  Q: Causes of prolonged jaundice in a neonate include all except?
  Expl snippet: Persistence of significant jaundice >2 weeks in term and >3 weeks in preterm babies is termed Prolonged Jaundice In A Ne...
ID: 23635 | Ans (A): Continue breastfeeding and observe
  Q: A 1-day-old newborn has not passed urine since birth. What is the most appropriate next step in management?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: If a healthy term neonate has not passed urine within the first 24 hours, the initial management is to cont...
ID: 23973 | Ans (C): JE
  Q: Which disease has not been covered routinely under Mission Indradhanush?
  Expl snippet: Mission Indradhanush was launched in December 2014 with the objective of achieving full immunization coverage for more t...
ID: 24091 | Ans (B): Neonatal hepatitis
  Q: A newborn presents with conjugated hyperbilirubinemia, intrahepatic cholestasis, elevated alkaline phosphatase, and eosi
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Neonatal hepatitis : Neonatal hepatitis is the most common cause of conjugated jaundice in newborns and may...
ID: 24114 | Ans (B): Transient tachypnea of newborn
  Q: A newborn delivered at 36 weeks has breathing difficulty which improved with Fi02 30%. Chest X-ray is shown below. What 
  Expl snippet: Explanation: A 36-week newborn with mild respiratory distress needing only 30 % FiO 2 and a chest X-ray showing fluid wi...
ID: 24189 | Ans (A): Most Common cause of Non-Syndromic SNHL 
  Q: Which of the following is true about Congenital CMV Infection?
  Expl snippet: Let us evaluate each option Option A is true. Congenital CMV is the most common non-syndromic cause of SNHL in children....
ID: 24226 | Ans (C): PP65 antigen levels
  Q: Which of the following is used to monitor response to therapy in a patient of severe congenital CMV, who is being treate
  Expl snippet: Fast detection methods for CMV viremia include: the antigenemia assay for detecting PP65 antigen in polymorphonuclear le...
ID: 24227 | Ans (B): Clutton's joints
  Q: Not a feature of early congenital syphilis?
  Expl snippet: Clutton&rsquo;s joints refers to bilateral knee swelling or effusion, seen in late congenital syphilis, appearing beyond...
ID: 24263 | Ans (C): A dried blood sample and screen first fo
  Q: A 22-year-old mother presented with her 2-week-old newborn who had a large tongue and an umbilical hernia. Which investi
  Expl snippet: Explanation: The clinical manifestations indicate congenital hypothyroidism, as evidenced by the large tongue and umbili...
ID: 24270 | Ans (D): Prolonged jaundice
  Q: During his 1st physical examination following birth at home with the assistance of a midwife, a 5- week-old male is susp
  Expl snippet: Prolongation of physiologic jaundice, due to delayed maturation of glucuronide conjugation, is often the 1st clinical fi...
ID: 24271 | Ans (B): 3 days
  Q: A full term baby born to a mother with hypothyroidism, needs to be screened for congenital hypothyroidism ideally at wha
  Expl snippet: A newborn screening for congenital hypothyroidism must be done at 3-4 days of life coupled with newborn screening for in...
ID: 24277 | Ans (A): CAH
  Q: A newborn infant is found at birth to have proximal hypospadias in a short phallus with bilateral nonpalpable gonads. Th
  Expl snippet: Child is genotypic female . Phenotypically child has ambiguous genitals as the phallus is small and gonads are non-palpa...
ID: 24283 | Ans (A): 21 hydroxylase
  Q: A female newborn is found to have ambiguous genitalia. Work up shows very high 17-hydroxyprogesterone and progesterone l
  Expl snippet: A female neonate with ambiguous genitalia is likely to have either 21 hydroxylase deficiency or 11 beta hydroxylase defi...
ID: 24304 | Ans (A): Neuroblastoma
  Q: A 4 year old boy is found to be having a large abdominal mass on routine examination. What is the next most common diffe
  Topic Tag: SOLID TUMORS Difficulty level: MUST KNOW PYQ: FMGE JULY 2023 Reference: Nelson textbook of paediatrics, 21 st ed, page number: 2681
  Expl snippet: Most common cause of renal mass in a preschool child is Nephroblastoma. Other renal causes of an abdominal mass include ...
ID: 24382 | Ans (B): You are unable to tell right now and a d
  Q: A newborn baby has recently been delivered. The midwife requests an urgent pediatric review of the baby because she cann
  Topic Tag: DISORDER OF SEXUAL DEVELOPMENT Difficulty level: MUST KNOW Reference: Nelson textbook of pediatrics, 21 st ed., pg. 3008
  Expl snippet: A detailed assessment by medical, surgical and psychological specialists needs to be performed followed by a full discus...
ID: 24430 | Ans (B): Stage 2
  Q: A neonate had delayed cry after birth and developed features of hypoxic ischemic encephalopathy (HIE). On examination, h
  Expl snippet: The features, especially the presence of recurrent focal seizures and miotic pupils, are suggestive of Stage 2 HIE. Plea...

======================================================
MODULE 576: Diseases in Neonates requiring Special Care (50 questions)
======================================================
ID: 2930 | Ans (B): Fat
  Q: Parenteral nutrition is instituted for a 4-day-old infant who has a total bilirubin of 18 mg/dL and a direct bilirubin o
  Expl snippet: Option B: Reason for Restriction: Infusion of lipids displaces bilirubin from albumin , increasing the risk of kernicter...
ID: 9377 | Ans (D): Cabergoline
  Q: A G2P1 delivered a preterm baby at 36 weeks. The baby was admitted to the NICU and given expressed breast milk. Unfortun
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Cabergoline is a potent dopamine D2 receptor agonist with minimal activity at D1, 5-HT, and &alpha;-adrener...
ID: 17563 | Ans (D): Juvenile chronic arthritis
  Q: A 14 year old boy has fevers. He has had elbow , shoulder and hip and knee pains over the last few months. On examinatio
  Expl snippet: Any arthritis that occurs in individuals Oligoarticular Polyarticular Rheumatoid factor positive Polyarticular Rheumatoi...
ID: 23345 | Ans (A): 2, 3
  Q: Which of the following children are considered at-risk babies? 1. Baby with a birth weight of 2.5 kg 2. Baby on artifici
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Among the given options, babies on artificial feeding and those with a working mother or single parent fall...
ID: 23382 | Ans (B): Observation
  Q: A 2700-gram, term baby, well and exclusively breastfed, was found to be icteric with a TSB of 14 mg/dl on day 5 of life.
  Expl snippet: Ideally decision to start phototherapy or exchange transfusion depends on American Academy of Pediatrics (AAP) Charts. P...
ID: 23383 | Ans (C): VZIG to baby + Acyclovir to mother as we
  Q: What is the therapy of choice in asymptomatic baby born to pregnant female who gets chicken pox one day prior to deliver
  Expl snippet: Mortality is particularly high in neonates born to susceptible mothers who contract varicella around the time of deliver...
ID: 23384 | Ans (D): Acyclovir is unsafe in neonates with sus
  Q: All of the following are true regarding management of chicken pox, except
  Expl snippet: Management of Chicken Pox/Varicella Management is symptomatic and includes antipyretics Aspirin is contraindicated due t...
ID: 23385 | Ans (C): Structural isomerization
  Q: Which mechanism of phototherapy is chiefly responsible for reduction in serum bilirubin?
  Expl snippet: Phototherapy (PTx) remains the mainstay of treating hyperbilirubinemia in neonates. PTx is highly effective and carries ...
ID: 23387 | Ans (C): Passing >4 stools in 24 hr
  Q: You are planning to discharge a neonate & explain danger signs to the parents, counselling them to bring the child to ho
  Expl snippet: Neonates can normally pass 6-8 stools in 24 hr and so passing >4 stools in 24 hr is not considered a danger sign. Danger...
ID: 23388 | Ans (B): Early rescue surfactant
  Q: A 31-week-old neonate was delivered via LSCS. Which among the following surfactant strategies shall be useful in such a 
  Expl snippet: Types of surfactant administration in RDS or suspected RDS in preterm neonates Prophylactic surfactant:- Surfactant is a...
ID: 23389 | Ans (C): Normal Saline Bolus
  Q: A neonate was resuscitated successfully but found to develop hypovolemic shock. What is the next step in management?
  Expl snippet: Some neonates can develop hypovolemic shock in the post-resuscitation phase or during resuscitation owing to excessive b...
ID: 23390 | Ans (C): 20 sec
  Q: What is the cut-off to define apnea in a neonate?
  Expl snippet: Apnea in neonates Defined as Stoppage or Cessation of breathing for &ge; 20 seconds in a neonate. Cessation of breathing...
ID: 23392 | Ans (C): MDI With Mask With Spacer
  Q: A child aged less than 1 yr of age is suspected to have an asthma-like illness and so was decided to start on therapy. W
  Expl snippet: Using Metered Dose Inhaler (MDI) with spacer to administer drugs via inhalational route has multiple advantages, like no...
ID: 23393 | Ans (C): Myotonic dystrophy
  Q: See the picture below and tell the likely diagnosis if child has muscular dystrophy, facial weakness and characteristic 
  Expl snippet: Facial weakness, inverted V-shaped upper lip, and loss Facial weakness, inverted V-shaped upper lip, and loss of muscle ...
ID: 23394 | Ans (D): Positive meningeal signs
  Q: Clinical features of meningitis in infancy include all the following except:
  Expl snippet: Meningeal signs are absent below months of age, even if the child has meningitis. Signs of meningitis in neonates and in...
ID: 23395 | Ans (B): Parvovirus B19
  Q: Which of the following microorganism is the most common cause of aplastic crisis in Sickle Cell Anemia & Hereditary Sphe
  Expl snippet: Human Parvovirus B19, also written as B19V, is notorious for aplastic crisis in chronic hemolytic states. Individuals wi...
ID: 23396 | Ans (B): Burkitt's lymphoma
  Q: A child with an underlying malignancy developed tumour lysis syndrome. Which among the following is the most likely such
  Expl snippet: Tumour lysis syndrome (TLS) is characterized by hyperuricemia, hyperkalemia, hyperphosphatemia, and hypocalcemia and is ...
ID: 23397 | Ans (A): Uncuffed tube is better than cuffed tube
  Q: All of the following are true regarding pediatric intubation, except?
  Expl snippet: Let us see all options individually Option A is false. Only in neonates, we prefer an uncuffed tube. Beyond the neonatal...
ID: 23398 | Ans (A): Coarctation of aorta
  Q: A Child presents with absent femoral pulses with increased blood pressure in the upper limbs and dilated intercostal art
  Expl snippet: The clinical picture is compatible with a diagnosis of Coarctation of aorta (CoA). CoA refers to narrowing or constricti...
ID: 23399 | Ans (C): Statement A, B
  Q: Choose the correct statement regarding physiological jaundice in neonates A. It is caused by inadequate hepatic conjugat
  Expl snippet: The exaggerated physiological jaundice in neonates is a result of increased RBC lysis along with low hepatic capacity to...
ID: 23400 | Ans (B): Varicella-zoster immune globulin
  Q: A 4-year-old boy with acute lymphocytic leukemia is currently receiving consolidation chemotherapy. His mother informs y
  Expl snippet: Passive immune-prophylaxis after exposure to varicella is indicated in immunocompromised patients, certain neonates, and...
ID: 23401 | Ans (B): Strangulated hernia
  Q: A 2-year-old child presents with a scrotal swelling since birth, which has recently become painful, red, and irreducible
  Expl snippet: Explanation: A strangulated inguinal hernia occurs when a loop of intestine enters the inguinal canal and becomes trappe...
ID: 23402 | Ans (C): ECF is higher than ICF
  Q: Children easily get dehydrated. What is the difference in the ECF and ICF ratio compared to that of adults?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: In neonates, extracellular fluid (ECF) volume is higher than intracellular fluid (ICF) By around 3 months o...
ID: 23403 | Ans (A): Cold temperature
  Q: Cutis marmorata is a condition seen in neonates due to exposure to?
  Expl snippet: Cutis marmorata is a condition seen in neonates due to exposure to cold temperature. Key takeaways:- ref :Nelson textboo...
ID: 23404 | Ans (A): 10 ml/kg
  Q: Child with polytrauma came to casualty, dose of packed cell
  Expl snippet: Answer-A Usual dosage of packed red cells in pediatric populations is 10-15 ml/kg, but can be increased upto 20 ml/kg in...
ID: 23405 | Ans (C): 12.5
  Q: Maximum concentration of dextrose that can be given through peripheral vascular line in neonate -
  Expl snippet: Ans. is 'c' i.e., 12.5 o Hypoglycemia in neonates is blood sugar 12.5% dextrose infusion through peripheral line because...
ID: 23418 | Ans (B): 2 weeks
  Q: Jaundice due to biliary atresia is suspected when it persists beyond?
  Expl snippet: Neonatal cholestasis tends to produce conjugated hyperbilirubinemia in a neonate & usually produces prolonged jaundice. ...
ID: 23419 | Ans (A): To determine gestational age
  Q: Look at the chart below and tell the use of this chart in neonates?
  Expl snippet: The given image shows Expanded New Ballard Score (ENBS), which is used to determine the gestational age of a neonate bas...
ID: 23422 | Ans (C): Start Phototherapy
  Q: A term baby born to primigravida mother with maternal blood group was found to be icteric on the very first day of life.
  Expl snippet: Any baby who has visible jaundice on day 1 of life, or has jaundice with encephalopathy or TcB value above 95 th percent...
ID: 23424 | Ans (A): Biliary atresia
  Q: A 2-week-old infant presents with high conjugated (direct) bilirubin, dark-colored urine, and clay-colored stools. On ex
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Biliary atresia is the most common cause of neonatal cholestasis . It presents in the first weeks of life w...
ID: 23435 | Ans (C): Acute chest syndrome
  Q: Usual indications for an exchange transfusion in a child with sickle cell disease include?
  Expl snippet: Indications for an exchange transfusion reaction in a child with sickle cell disease may include Acute CNS event (stroke...
ID: 23440 | Ans (B): Biliary atresia
  Q: Which is NOT a feature of cystic fibrosis?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Biliary atresia is not a feature of cystic fibrosis (CF) . CF can lead to liver disease and biliary cirrhos...
ID: 23441 | Ans (D): Biliary atresia
  Q: A 3-month-old infant presents to the pediatric OPD with complaints of persistent jaundice and pale (clay-colored) stools
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Biliary atresia presents in infancy with conjugated hyperbilirubinemia, clay-colored stools, and shows peri...
ID: 23443 | Ans (D): CO2 washout
  Q: A child with PDA will not have which among the following?
  Expl snippet: Children with PDA have pulmonary congestion due to increased pulmonary blood flow, which results in CO2 Retention, not C...
ID: 23445 | Ans (C): Choreo-athetoid CP
  Q: A term neonate with Rh incompatibility developed severe unconjugated hyperbilirubinemia. The baby was managed with photo
  Expl snippet: Interpretation The baby had features of pathological unconjugated hyperbilirubinemia Later he developed seizures, deafne...
ID: 23446 | Ans (A): CHPS
  Q: 24 day neonate with projectile vomiting & failure to gain weight .what is the diagnosis
  Expl snippet: Answer- A. CHPS Projectile vomiting in 4th week is quite suggestive of CHPS. In duodenal atresia the vomiting (usually b...
ID: 23447 | Ans (B): 5-10 ml/min
  Q: Blood transfusion to neonate rate of
  Expl snippet: Answer- B. 5-10 ml/min A) Exchange transfusion For term infant = 80-160 ml/kg For pre term = 100-200 ml/kg B) Top-up tra...
ID: 23672 | Ans (B): Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy
  Q: Dystrophin protein is absent completely in which of the following diseases?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Duchenne Muscular Dystrophy (DMD) is a genetic disorder caused by mutations in the dystrophin gene, resulti...
ID: 23709 | Ans (B): Hemorrhagic disease of the newborn
  Q: Vitamin K supplementation is given to neonates to prevent:
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Vitamin K is essential for blood clotting, and its deficiency can lead to hemorrhagic disease of the newbor...
ID: 23821 | Ans (A): Congenital Heart Disease
  Q: Down syndrome patients are found to have a reduced life expectancy compared to the general population. Which among the f
  Expl snippet: As per OP Ghai 10th Edition, the chief cause of early mortality in Down Syndrome patients is Congenital Heart Disease. F...
ID: 23858 | Ans (D): Methionine
  Q: Which amino acid does not need to be restricted in diet in MSUD?
  Expl snippet: Maple Syrup Urine Disease (MSUD) AR inheritance Defect in decarboxylation of branched chain Amino acids Valine,Leucine &...
ID: 23876 | Ans (A): Rett syndrome
  Q: Which of the following diseases is X linked dominant?
  Expl snippet: Mnemonic for conditions with X-linked dominant inheritance: "Red Ribbon For All Children" Rickets (Hypophosphatemic) Ret...
ID: 24033 | Ans (C): Parvovirus B19
  Q: Perinatal infection presenting with anemia, possible myocarditis, high-output cardiac failure, and ascites is most likel
  Expl snippet: Explanation: The clinical features described - anemia, myocarditis, high-output cardiac failure, and ascites in the cont...
ID: 24040 | Ans (D): Hand foot and mouth disease
  Q: Which of the following diseases presents with ulcers and blisters in children?
  Expl snippet: Kyasanur forest disease and Zika virus presents with maculo-papular rashes. Erythema infectiosum has a slapped cheek app...
ID: 24044 | Ans (B): Congenital diaphragmatic hernia
  Q: Bag and mask ventilation is absolutely contraindicated in neonates due to?
  Expl snippet: Bag and mask ventilation (BMV) is absolutely contraindicated in Congenital Diaphragmatic Hernia (CDH) and relatively con...
ID: 24063 | Ans (A): In the mid epigastric area
  Q: A 4-week-old child presents to the hospital with a complaint of projectile, non-bilious vomiting associated with movable
  Expl snippet: In the given scenario of projectile, non-bilious vomiting and a movable, olive-shaped abdominal mass, the most probable ...
ID: 24089 | Ans (A): Kasai procedure should be done within 90
  Q: Which of the following is false regarding neonatal cholestasis?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: The Kasai portoenterostomy (hepaticojejunostomy) is most successful when performed within the first 60 days...
ID: 24165 | Ans (A): Diazepam
  Q: A 6-year-old child is brought to the emergency department with continuous generalized tonic-clonic seizures lasting for 
  Expl snippet: Explanation: The child is in status epilepticus (SE) - defined as continuous seizure activity >5 minutes or recurrent se...
ID: 24336 | Ans (C): Purulent conjunctivitis
  Q: Which of the following is not seen in Kawasaki diseases?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Kawasaki disease features bilateral non-purulent conjunctivitis. Kawasaki Disease Diagnostic Criteria (CREA...
ID: 24571 | Ans (C): 1 and 3
  Q: A 4-month-old infant is brought to the OPD with intense itching, especially at night. On examination, there are multiple
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Permethrin 5% and Crotamiton 10% are used to treat scabies in infants. Permethrin 5% cream is the preferred...

======================================================
MODULE 577: Apgar score and Neonatal Resuscitation (50 questions)
======================================================
ID: 17264 | Ans (A): Control of fever
  Q: Treatment of simple febrile convulsion is based on
  Expl snippet: Answer- A. Control of fever Prompt reduction of temperature by hydrotherapy (sponging) and antipyretics (paracetamole, i...
ID: 17381 | Ans (A): DMD
  Q: Dystrophin absent and presence of small muscle fibrils cause?
  Expl snippet: Duchenne and Becker muscular dystrophy are the Dystrophinopaties. DMD is characterized by absent dystrophin and Becker's...
ID: 18531 | Ans (D): Rett syndrome
  Q: Cannabinoid oil not indicated in which of the following conditions?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Cannabidiol (CBD) oil , a non-psychoactive compound derived from the cannabis plant, has been FDA-approved ...
ID: 18570 | Ans (A): Periventricular leukomalacia
  Q: A patient presents with spastic quadriplegia. What is the most likely site of lesion?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Periventricular leukomalacia (PVL) refers to ischemic necrosis of the white matter adjacent to the lateral ...
ID: 23346 | Ans (C): Symmetric tonic neck reflex
  Q: Neonatal reflex which is not present at birth?
  Expl snippet: All primitive reflexes are present at birth in a term neonate except Symmetric tonic neck reflex Parachute reflex Landau...
ID: 23366 | Ans (B): Polyhydramnios
  Q: A baby is born at 43 w 4 d of gestational age. Which of the following morbidity is not to be anticipated in this baby?
  Expl snippet: Morbidities associated with post-term pregnancy include the presence of Meconium-stained amniotic fluid ( option a) Meco...
ID: 23413 | Ans (A): Acinetobacter
  Q: Which among the following is the most common cause of neonatal sepsis in India?
  Expl snippet: As per the data mentioned in the latest AIIMS Neonatal Protocols, 3 rd Edition, Acinetobacter (22%), Klebsiella (17%), S...
ID: 23414 | Ans (A): Transcranial ultrasound
  Q: A 2-day old neonate in the neonatal ICU develops seizures. Which of the following would be the next best investigation f
  Expl snippet: In such a situation, BEDSIDE CRANIAL USG is a very useful and informative investigation. Cranial Ultrasound (CUS) in neo...
ID: 23415 | Ans (D): Exstrophy bladder
  Q: Which neonatal anomaly is depicted in the image?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Exstrophy bladder is a congenital anomaly where the bladder mucosa is exposed outside the abdominal wall du...
ID: 23417 | Ans (A): Acute bilirubin encephalopathy stage 2
  Q: A neonate born at term to A-ve mother was found to have neonatal jaundice on day 1 but no medical attention was taken. 8
  Expl snippet: The child is showing retrocollis and opisthotonus posturing, seen in acute bilirubin encephalopathy stage 2. Stages of a...
ID: 23420 | Ans (B): Group B streptococcus
  Q: Most common cause of neonatal sepsis worldwide/overall?
  Expl snippet: According to Nelson 21 st Edition, The most common causes of neonatal sepsis in the western World are Group B Streptococ...
ID: 23421 | Ans (B): Neutrophilia
  Q: All of the following are consistent in neonatal sepsis except?
  Expl snippet: Children with neonatal sepsis more likely have neutropenia than neutrophilia. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) less than ...
ID: 23423 | Ans (D): Color of skin
  Q: While giving phototherapy to a neonate for neonatal jaundice, the effectiveness of phototherapy depends on all except
  Expl snippet: The therapeutic effect of phototherapy depends on Light energy emitted in the effective range of wavelengths, Distance b...
ID: 23427 | Ans (A): Retinopathy of prematurity
  Q: Ranibizumab is useful in the management of which of the following neonatal conditions?
  Expl snippet: Intravitreal Anti-VEGF Drugs In Neonatology Anti-VEGF drugs like bevacizumab or ranibizumab when injected directly into ...
ID: 23448 | Ans (C): 3, 4
  Q: In a newborn delivered through meconium-stained amniotic fluid, which of the following steps are recommended according t
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Management of meconium-stained liquor depends on whether the neonate is vigorous or non-vigorous. Vigorous ...
ID: 23449 | Ans (C): Initiate bag-and-mask ventilation
  Q: A full-term infant born through emergency cesarean section to a 34-year-old mother whose pregnancy was complicated by hy
  Expl snippet: In a baby born through meconium-stained liquor (MSL), we evaluate if the baby is vigorous or not. In a vigorous baby, on...
ID: 23450 | Ans (A): Congenital diaphragmatic hernia
  Q: You are called to the nursery to assess a newborn girl. She was born at 39 weeks via normal spontaneous delivery to a mo
  Expl snippet: The newborn girl has findings that are suggestive of congenital diaphragmatic hernia. Congenital diaphragmatic hernia (C...
ID: 23452 | Ans (C): Positive-Pressure Ventilation in all non
  Q: True regarding management and resuscitation in a baby born through meconium-stained liquor (MSL)?
  Expl snippet: Let us evaluate the options sequentially Option A is False- Intrapartum suctioning is not indicated anymore in neonates ...
ID: 23455 | Ans (D): CMV
  Q: A female delivered a 1.2 kg baby prematurely at 31 wk. The child has hepatosplenomegaly, jaundice, petechial rash. The c
  Expl snippet: Clues in the question Preterm delivery Periventricular calcification Hepatosplenomegaly with jaundice Petechial Rash Fai...
ID: 23456 | Ans (D): HR<60/min with Chest Compressions & PPV 
  Q: In a neonate undergoing resuscitation, PPV and chest compressions are being administered. Epinephrine should be administ
  Expl snippet: Medications are rarely required in neonatal resuscitation since the mainstay of management is adequate ventilation with ...
ID: 23457 | Ans (C): Right upper limb
  Q: A neonate was born at term and did not cry after birth. Resuscitation was started and baby was connected to ECG and SPO2
  Expl snippet: An oximeter should be used to confirm the perception of cyanosis, when PPV is required for more than a few breaths, when...
ID: 23458 | Ans (C): 8
  Q: Calculate the APGAR score in a neonate at 1 min of life, if there is acrocyanosis, grimacing on examination, HR is 110/m
  Expl snippet: APGAR Score Reference: OP Ghai 10 th Edition, Page 121, Table 9.2...
ID: 23459 | Ans (D): Hypotonia
  Q: Which of the following is an effective indicator or perinatal asphyxia?
  Expl snippet: Essential Criteria For Perinatal Asphyxia Prolonged Metabolic or Mixed Acidemia (pH Persistence of APGAR Score of 0-3 fo...
ID: 23460 | Ans (C): Lambdoid suture
  Q: Not involved in anterior fontanelle formation?
  Expl snippet: Look at the image showing the neonatal skull. Reference: Nelson 21 st Edition, Chapter 608...
ID: 23461 | Ans (B): Improvement in HR
  Q: Which of the following is the best way to assess adequate response of ventilation during neonatal resuscitation?
  Expl snippet: After birth, the newborn's heart rate is used to assess the effectiveness of spontaneous respiratory effort, the need fo...
ID: 23462 | Ans (A): Start BMV on room air
  Q: A neonate delivered at term did not cry or breath at birth. Initial Steps were performed and the child's HR was found to
  Expl snippet: As per Neonatal Resuscitation Guidelines, PPV using BMV is the most important step, which is done after initial Steps. P...
ID: 23463 | Ans (D): Begin chest compressions
  Q: A term baby is born after an uncomplicated pregnancy to a 33-year-old mother. At birth he was lethargic and had an HR of
  Expl snippet: Based on the neonatal resuscitation algorithm, if the HR is still less than 60 beats/min despite positive-pressure venti...
ID: 23465 | Ans (B): Mouth &rarr; Nose
  Q: Correct order of suctioning during neonatal resuscitation is?
  Expl snippet: As part of the initial steps of neonatal resuscitation, we need to suction the secretions, if present. Always suction mo...
ID: 23466 | Ans (D): Severely Depressed
  Q: You are an intern reading the birth card of an infant. You find that the report mentions APGAR Score of 3 at 1 minute. T
  Expl snippet: APGAR Score APGAR is routinely measured at 1 min and 5 min. 0-3 = Severely depressed 4-6 = Moderately depressed 7-10 = N...
ID: 23467 | Ans (B): Phenobarbitone
  Q: Drug of choice for neonatal seizures is?
  Expl snippet: Phenobarbitone is the drug of choice in neonatal seizures. The dose is 20 mg/kg/IV slowly over 20 minutes (not faster th...
ID: 23468 | Ans (A): 3:1
  Q: During neonatal resuscitation, while giving chest compression what should be the ratio of chest compression to bag and m
  Expl snippet: The chest compression to breathing ratio must be maintained as 3:1 in newborns. It is 15:2 in children for two rescuers ...
ID: 23469 | Ans (D): 0.05-0.1 mg/kg
  Q: What is the proper dose of adrenaline to be used during neonatal resuscitation if given endotracheally?
  Expl snippet: Adrenaline must be administered by IV route at 0.01-0.03mg/kg if venous access is available. If IV access is difficult, ...
ID: 23470 | Ans (C): 9
  Q: A 38 week, 3.2kg baby boy is born by spontaneous vaginal delivery. At 5 minutes he has a heart rate over 100, is crying 
  Expl snippet: Tags : Topic : Normal Newborn; APGAR Difficulty level : Must know PYQ : NEET PG 2019; INICET MAY 2022 Reference : Cloher...
ID: 23471 | Ans (D): Preterm gestation
  Q: A 34-week-gestation neonate is admitted to the NICU with respiratory distress. The mother's pregnancy was complicated by
  Expl snippet: Early-onset sepsis (EOS) continues to be a significant source of neonatal morbidity and mortality. Risk factor for Early...
ID: 23473 | Ans (B): 60
  Q: Per the neonatal resuscitation guidelines, at what heart rate should chest compressions be started?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Per the Neonatal Resuscitation Program (NRP) guidelines, chest compressions should be started if the newbor...
ID: 23474 | Ans (B): 3
  Q: A baby assessed five minutes after birth is found to have a blue, absent pulse, minimal response to stimulation, slightl
  Expl snippet: Explanation: APGAR score: The APGAR score is an objective method of evaluating the newborn's condition. It is performed ...
ID: 23476 | Ans (C): Severely depressed
  Q: APGAR score of 3 at 1 minute indicates?
  Expl snippet: Nelson...
ID: 23477 | Ans (D): Slapping the back
  Q: Resuscitation of a neonate with HR < 60/min includes all of the following except?
  Expl snippet: In early part of resuscitation we do perform initial steps I)Maintain temperature/provide warmth to child ii)Dry the chi...
ID: 23478 | Ans (D): Hypotonia
  Q: Which of the following is an effective indicator of perinatal asphyxia?
  Expl snippet: Essential Criteria For Perinatal Asphyxia Prolonged Metabolic or Mixed Acidemia (pH Persistence of APGAR Score of 0-3 fo...
ID: 23479 | Ans (B): Improvement in HR
  Q: Which of the following is the best way to assess adequate response of ventilation during neonatal resuscitation?
  Expl snippet: Improvement in HR is the most important indicator to assess adequate response of ventilation during neonatal resuscitati...
ID: 23480 | Ans (C): 1000 ml bolus then regulated by clinical
  Q: Polytrauma patient came to EMS, dose of crystalloid given should be
  Expl snippet: Answer- C. 1000 ml bolus then regulated by clinical indicators Fluid resuscitation begins with 1000 ml bolus of RL for a...
ID: 23481 | Ans (C): 0.1-0.3 ml/kg in 1:10,000
  Q: Dose of i.v. adrenaline in term infant is during neonatal resuscitation -
  Expl snippet: Ans. is c i.e., 0.1-0.3 mUkg in 1:10,000 Dose or adrenlaine ? 0.1 ml/kg to 0.3 inlikg diluted (1: I0,000) Routs : (1) In...
ID: 23482 | Ans (B): 125 mg/dl
  Q: Hyperglycemia in Neonate if blood sugar is above ?
  Expl snippet: Ans. is 'b' i.e., 125 mg/dl o No established definition of neonatal hyperglycemia and upper safe limit of blood glucose ...
ID: 23483 | Ans (D): All the above
  Q: Of the following, causes of neonatal seizures is/are?
  Expl snippet: Hypoglycemia, hypocalcemia, hypomagnesemia, and hyponatremia account for approximately 5% of neonatal seizures. Referenc...
ID: 23484 | Ans (C): Bolus of 10 ml/kg
  Q: A child with 20% burns is noted to have low urine output after 6 hours of resuscitation and has cool extremities. What i
  Expl snippet: Explanation: In children with significant burns (>15-20% TBSA), fluid resuscitation is guided by formulas such as the Pa...
ID: 23523 | Ans (A): Macrocephaly
  Q: Which of the following is not one of the neonatal finding due to varicella infection in mother during pregnancy?
  Expl snippet: Features associated with congenital varicella are: Cicatricial skin lesions- Dermatomal distribution Ocular defects like...
ID: 23936 | Ans (B): Cephalosporins are the drug of choice
  Q: Choose the false statement regarding neonatal tetanus
  Expl snippet: It occurs in unimmunized mothers The contamination of umbilical stump during delivery is important cause. Usually presen...
ID: 24167 | Ans (C): Endotracheal intubation and chest compre
  Q: A 38 week term baby is delivered by emergency cesarean section due to non reassuring doppler findings. The baby did not 
  Expl snippet: Tags : Topic : NEONATAL RESUSCITATION Difficulty level : MUST KNOW PYQ : INICET MAY 2022; FMGE JAN 2023; JUNE 2022; JULY...
ID: 24264 | Ans (D): 72 hours after delivery
  Q: When is a blood sample taken for diagnosing neonatal hypothyroidism?
  Expl snippet: Explanation: Serum TSH levels are typically measured between 2 to 4 days of life for the screening of congenital hypothy...
ID: 24265 | Ans (D): 72 hrs after birth
  Q: Blood specimen for neonatal thyroid screening is obtained at?
  Expl snippet: Screening for congenital hypothyroidism is done by heel pad prick, beyond 48 hr of life, ideally AT 72 HOURS. Some texts...
